Finding Aid for Nichols & Shepard Company records, 1873-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nichols & Shepard Company records 1873-1931
Nichols & Shepard Company.
12 oversize volumes
4 linear feet
85711 Bb.2 2; BB.2 Outsize
Manufacturers of threshing machinery; company sold out to Oliver Corporation in 1929. Minutes of stockholders and directors meetings, journals, ledgers, balance sheets, correspondence, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group came from Louis Ryason (donor no. 3998 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Nichols & Shepard Company of Battle Creek Company was established in 1848 by John Nichols and Charles H. Shepard as a manufacturer of threshing machinery. In 1929, the company sold out to the Oliver Tractor Company.
The Nichols & Shepard Company records date from the late nineteenth century to the time when the company sold out to the Oliver Corporation. There is very little material prior to the 1880s and thus the first thirty years of the company's history is without documentation. The minutes of the company's board of directors date back to 1886 and extend to 1931. A large portion of the record group consists of financial materials, reports, and ledgers.
Subjects:
Agricultural machinery industry--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Oliver Corporation.; Nichols & Shepard Company.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agricultural machinery.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Nichols & Shepard Company.; Oliver Corporation.; Railroads--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Business records.
- Board of Directors
  - Minute Book 1886-1913 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - 1913 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1914 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1914 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1914 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1915 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1915 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1915 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1916 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1916 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1916 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1917 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1917 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1917 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1918 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1918 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1918 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1919 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1919 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1919 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1920 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1920 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1920 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1921 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1921 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1921 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1922 (Box 1)
    - May-August 1922 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1922 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1923 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1923 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1924 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1924 (Box 1)
  - Minute Book 1928-1931 (Box 1)
- Other records
  - Minutes of special, stockholders meeting 1927 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and other papers
    - 1898-1901 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1925-1931
      - 1925-1927 (Box 2)
      - 1928, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1929, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1930-1931 (Box 2)
  - Contract between the National City Company and the Oliver Agricultural Equipment Company 1929 (Box 2)
  - Contract between the Nichols and Shepard Company and the Oliver Agricultural Equipment Company 1929 (Box 2)
  - Engine Memorandum 1887-1893, 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - Separator Memorandum 1879-1885 (Box 2)
  - Separator Memorandum 1894-1895 (Box 2)
  - Financial reports 1919-1922, 1928, 5 volumes (Box 3)
  - Certified Balance Sheets 1915-1928, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Financial reports 1926-1927, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Survey of Stores Department 1929 (Box 3)
  - Analysis of Repossessed Machinery 1925 (Box 3)
  - Specifications for wrecking and general excavation for a new warehouse 1928 (Box 3)
  - Register of stockholders 1887-1914 (Box 3)
  - Papers concerning property owned by Nichols and Shepard (Box 3)
  - Repair Price Lists 1910-1928, 12 volumes (Box 3)
  - Stockholders ledger (Box 3)
  - Sundry Debtors Ledgers 1926-1929, 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - General Ledger Transfers 1912-1928, 5 volumes (Volume 1)
  - Repair record 1927-1929 (Volume 2)
  - Detail cost sheets 1930, 2 volumes (Volume 3)
  - Cash blotter 1908-1920 (Volume 4)
  - Journal 1873-1920 (Volume 5)
  - General Ledger 1873-1920 (Volume 6)
  - Private Ledger 1887-1924 (Volume 7)
  - Four Plats of the Nichols and Shepard property (Box 5)
  - Photographs: photograph of train carrying farm equipment and portraits of officers of the company (Box 5)
Related Material
There are some Nichols and Shepard Company materials at Michigan State University Historical Collection.